this is our last video talking about the
basics of spinners in 3D space and 4D
space time from a mathematical point of
view and we're going to talk about a
deep concept we've been approaching for
a while called the double cover which
leads to the notion of a spin group this
will set the stage for the next set of
videos in the series where we discuss
Clifford algebras also called geometric
algebras
over the last few videos we showed how
3D vectors are rotated with the special
orthogonal 3x3 matrices SO3
we also showed that there was an
alternative way of doing rotations where
the vector was written as a two by two
Matrix called a Pali vector and is
rotated with a double-sided
transformation using special unitary 2x2
matrices su2
as I mentioned in video 6.1 the su-2
matrices are completely equivalent to
unit quaternions so I'll be talking
about them in this video as well
we say that the su2 matrices are the
double cover of SO3 matrices because for
every 3x3 rotation Matrix R there are a
pair of su2 matrices plus u and minus U
that perform the same rotation
because the transformation is
double-sided if we replace plus u with
minus U the two minus signs will cancel
out leading to the same transformation
we started with
this is an algebraic view of what it
means for su2 to be the double cover of
SO3
however there is also a topological
interpretation for this concept of a
double cover
topology is an area of math that's
sometimes called rubber sheet geometry
because it involves studying the overall
shape and connectedness of various
spaces without worrying about exact
sizes and angles
when we study the topology of SO3 or su2
we're studying the shape of what these
spaces of rotations look like and how
the space is connected with itself
it turns out that the space of su2
matrices looks like a three-dimensional
sphere that lives in four-dimensional
space called the three sphere or S3 for
short
this is a simplified view that looks
more like a two-dimensional sphere
because a true three-dimensional sphere
is too difficult to draw a true three
sphere has points that are specified by
three angles instead of two angles
the space of SO3 matrices looks like a
real projective three space rp3 which
sort of looks like half of a three
sphere where if we walk off one Edge we
get teleported to the other side
let's try and understand what these
spaces look like
it can be pretty difficult to get an
intuition for what we mean when we say
su2 is the three sphere and SO3 is real
projective three space and to understand
why one is the double cover of the other
these spaces are too high dimensional to
easily visualize so let's start simple
by working with the one sphere which is
the circle and real projective line and
work our way up from there we've already
discussed the real projective line in
video 5 in this series if we start with
the 2D plane and draw a vertical screen
at x equals one we can project points
onto the screen by drawing lines that
connect points to the origin and seeing
where these lines intersect the screen
the resulting space on the screen is
called the real projective line rp1
if we draw a circle centered at the
origin and try projecting various points
on the circle onto the screen we find
that opposite points on the circle exist
on the same line through the origin and
so they will get projected to the same
point on the screen this means that for
every one point in the real projective
line there are two points on the circle
for this reason we say that the circle
S1 is the double cover of the real
projective line rp1
if I do a single loop around the real
projective line we only cover half of
the circle It Takes Two Full loops
around the real projective line to cover
the full circle
so the real projective line is a bit
like a half circle where walking off one
Edge immediately teleports you to the
other side
a given point on the real projective
line can be described by a ratio of X Y
coordinates
any points with the same y over X ratio
will be connected by the same line
through the origin and so are projected
to the same point on the real projective
line
this pattern extends in higher
Dimensions if we start in 3D space and
place a 2d screen at x equals one and
then project points onto the screen
along lines through the origin the
screen ends up being the real projective
plane rp2
if we take a sphere centered at the
origin and project its points onto the
plane we find that opposite points on
the sphere exist on the same line
through the origin and so they get
projected to the same point on the real
projective plane
so for every point on the real
projective plane there are a pair of
points on the two sphere that get
projected to it and so we say that the
two sphere is the double cover of rp2
the real projective plane can be thought
of like a half sphere where walking off
the edge immediately teleports you to
the opposite Edge
points in the real projective plane can
be described by a pair of ratios y over
x and z over X any points in
three-dimensional space with these same
ratios will exist along the same line
through the origin and so they will get
projected to the same point on the real
projective plane
this pattern continues in the next
Dimension with the three sphere which is
too high dimensional for us to visualize
but we can describe it with an equation
the real projective three space rp3 is
also too high dimensional for us to
visualize however we can think of it as
the three sphere with opposite points
projected to the same point in
three-dimensional space
points in real projective three space
can be described by three ratios y over
X Z over X and W over X
any points in four-dimensional space
that have the same three ratios will
exist along the same line through the
origin and so they will get projected to
the same point in real projective three
space
rp3 can be thought of as half of a three
sphere where if we walk off the edge we
get immediately teleported to the other
side
so what does this have to do with su2
matrices being the double cover of SO3
matrices
well it turns out that su2 is shaped
like the three sphere and SO3 is shaped
like the real projective three space
we'll show this starting with su2 let's
take a 2x2 matrix with complex entries
Alpha Beta Gamma Delta
if this Matrix is unitary it means the
Matrix is hermitian conjugate is equal
to its inverse
taking the hermitian conjugate is easy
it's just the complex conjugate
transpose and the formula for the
inverse of a two by two Matrix is well
known
if the Matrix is special this means the
determinant equals plus one and so we
can take the determinant part of the
formula and set it to plus one
so for special unitary two by two
matrices we end up with gamma equals
negative beta complex conjugate and
Delta equals Alpha complex conjugate
so this is the form of an su2 Matrix
defined by two complex numbers Alpha and
beta
but remember the determinant equals plus
one so alpha alpha Star Plus beta beta
star must equal one
if we replace Alpha with the complex
number A plus b i and replace beta with
the complex number c plus d i and
distribute we end up with the formula a
squared plus b squared plus c squared
plus d squared equals one
if we think of a b c and d as coordinate
variables in four-dimensional space this
is the equation for a three-dimensional
sphere
there are three free parameters once we
specify a b and c then D is
automatically determined by the equation
so the three sphere is a
three-dimensional Space parameterized by
three coordinates this makes sense since
su2 is the space of three possible
rotations in the X Y plane the y z plane
and the ZX plane
now recall I said that when it comes to
double-sided Transformations the su2
matrices plus u and minus U will do the
same rotation because the negative signs
will always cancel out in a double-sided
transformation
so if we think of our three sphere the
matrices plus u and minus U would be on
opposite sides and they perform the
exact same rotation
if we can imagine projecting plus u and
minus U along the same line through the
origin onto a screen the result would be
a point in real projective three space
rp3 which is when we have a
three-dimensional screen living in
four-dimensional space
this point corresponds to the SO3
rotation Matrix R which does the same
rotation as both plus u and minus U
remember there are two su-2 matrices for
every SO3 Matrix that performs the same
rotation both plus u and minus U perform
the same rotation as r
the SO3 group is what we get when we
simply forget about the differences
between plus u and minus U and treat
them as the same rotation r
this is why SO3 has the shape of real
projective three space
this brings up a key difference between
the topologies of su2 and SO3 su2 has
the property of being a Simply Connected
space whereas SO3 is not a Simply
Connected space I'll explain what this
means
Loosely speaking a space is Simply
Connected if it has no holes or handles
one way to test if a space is Simply
Connected is to draw a loop starting and
ending at the same base point then check
if we can continuously shrink the loop
to a single point at the base point
if all such Loops can be contracted the
space is Simply Connected
if the space has holes or handles we
will be able to draw Loops that cannot
be continuously shrunk to a single point
all spheres with Dimension equal to or
greater than two are Simply Connected
it should be obvious on the two sphere
that any Loop we draw can be contracted
to a point
the same is true for the three sphere
and all higher dimensional spheres
the exception is the one sphere or
Circle which is not Simply Connected
since the three sphere is Simply
Connected this means that the space of
su2 matrices or unit quaternions is also
Simply Connected
real projective spaces are not Simply
Connected for example the real
projective plane rp2 is a sphere with
opposite points made equivalent if we
have a loop like this that we try to
contract if we contract part of the loop
the opposite end of the loop will run
away in the opposite direction because
opposite points on the sphere are
equivalent therefore Loops like this
cannot be continuously shrunk to a point
the same is true for real projective
space rp3 which is the space of SO3
matrices
so the space of SO3 matrices is not
Simply Connected
the topology of spaces of rotations can
be useful to think about for example
it's common to think of rotations in 3D
space as a combination of three rotation
angles one for each axis these are the
so-called Euler angles with each angle
being on a circle from 0 to 360 degrees
however this system has flaws in
particular the order of the rotation
angles matters
rotating around X and then Y is not the
same thing as rotating around Y and then
X
this awkwardness is reflected in the
topology of Euler angles the combination
of two rotation angles or two circles
gives a space that looks like a Taurus
and the combination of three rotation
angles or three circles gives us a
three-dimensional torus T3 this is not
equivalent to the real projective space
rp3 or its double cover S3
points in rp3 or S3 immediately specify
the correct axis and angle we need to do
the rotation instead of providing three
separate rotations and assuming there is
a specific order or priority in the
angle coordinates
the idea of double covers doesn't just
apply to 3D space we can also apply it
to 4D space time
if you watched video 9 in this series
you'll recall that in the
four-dimensional space time of special
relativity lorentz Transformations are
done with so13 matrices
these are matrices that keep the
space-time interval s squared constant
and forbid spatial Reflections since the
determinant is plus one
we can also enforce the ortho Cronus
property which means there are no time
Reflections by forcing the zero zero
component of the Matrix to be positive
the plus superscript Above So indicates
we're including this condition of no
time Reflections I'm going to assume
this orthochronous condition applies for
the rest of this video
we also learned that we could rewrite 4D
space-time vectors as two by two
matrices called vial vectors and we
could lorentz transform those with
double-sided Transformations involving
special linear two by two complex
matrices sl2c
this means that sl2c is the double cover
of so13 as there are two sl2c matrices
for every so13 Matrix that performs the
same Lorenz transformation
again negative signs will cancel out in
double-sided transformations
so11 is the set of lorentz
transformations in one time Dimension
and one space dimension
this set of Transformations gives a
hyperbola which extends infinitely in
either direction
hyperbolas are transformed with
hyperbolic rotations using hyperbolic
cosine and hyperbolic sine these are
also called lorentz boosts
this is different than the set of
rotations into spatial Dimensions SO2
which gives a circle transformed with
circular trig functions
hyperbolas have the topological property
of being non-compact which Loosely means
that they go on forever so hyperbolic
angles range from negative Infinity to
positive Infinity
this is unlike circles which are Compact
and have a finite extent and so circular
angles will loop back on themselves
so12 is the set of lorentz
transformations in one time Dimension
and two space dimensions
we now have two spatial Dimensions we
can boost in given by two hyperbolas and
we can also rotate around in a circle in
the two spatial Dimensions this gives us
a hyperboloid sheet
in contrast SO3 is the group of
rotational symmetries of 3D space which
is given by the three possible rotations
of the two sphere
so13 is the set of lorentz
transformations in one time Dimension
and three spatial dimensions
I can't draw this but it would be a
higher dimensional hyperboloid with
three possible hyperbola boosts and
three possible circles to rotate in
in contrast so4 is the group of rotation
symmetries of 4D space which is the six
possible rotations of the three sphere
sl2c is the double cover of so13 and is
given by a set of six basic 2x2 matrices
that operate on Spinners on the Block
sphere
three of these matrices do the basic
rotations of the block sphere that we're
familiar with
but there are also three boost matrices
which can also transform the block
sphere
if we boost in the plus Z Direction then
the plus Z and minus said Spinners stay
fixed circles centered around the z-axis
are pushed in the direction of the
negative Z spinner as we continue
boosting
there is a similar effect for X boosts
and Y boosts
as an exercise you can try coming up
with a mathematical argument for why
these matrices push circles in One
Direction on the Block sphere you can
look at the limiting behaviors of
hyperbolic sine and hyperbolic cosine to
help you
keep in mind overall scaling and phases
don't matter for Spinners on the Block
sphere
recall two spinners are mathematically
orthogonal if they point in opposite
directions on the Block sphere this is
because opposite directions on the Block
sphere represent two mutually exclusive
measurement states in the stern gerlock
experiment
you'll notice that if we have two
spinners that are orthogonal and then we
perform a boost operation on the sphere
it is possible that the Spinners are no
longer orthogonal after the Boost this
would seem to violate Bourne's rule
which says that probabilities and
quantum mechanics are directly related
to the angle between State vectors
if we do a boost two spinners can be
orthogonal in one frame but be
non-orthogonal in another frame
this makes it seem like quantum
mechanics is not compatible with lorentz
boosts from special relativity this is
one of the challenges that comes with
uniting quantum mechanics with special
relativity this contradiction is solved
in Quantum field Theory where we treat
particles as excitations in fields that
extend all throughout space which
include position degrees of freedom as
well as rotational degrees of freedom
however I won't be talking about that in
this video
I'll mention one last thing about sl2c
which is how it relates to Mobius
transformations
recall that for Spinners that represent
Quantum States overall multiplication by
a non-zero complex number doesn't change
the quantum State because these overall
factors are canceled out in the
normalized born's rule
because of this Spinners are completely
defined by the ratio of their two
components
let's take a two component spinner with
components PSI and transform it by a two
by two Matrix to give another two
component spinner with components PSI
tilde
since only the ratio of the output
components matters we can write the
matrix multiplication as a pair of
equations and take their ratio
we can also multiply the numerator and
denominator by 1 over PSI 2 to give us
ratios of the input components
I'm going to write this ratio of input
components as Z and the ratio of output
components as Z tilde
this is an alternative way of writing
Transformations on spinners and it's
called a Mobius transformation also
called a fractional linear
transformation
notice that if we take the Matrix
coefficients and multiply them by an
arbitrary complex number this will not
affect the Mobius transformation since
the factors will cancel out in the
fraction formula
this means that any matrices that differ
by an overall multiplication of a
complex number perform the same
transformation
this allows us to scale the matrices by
any complex number we like and therefore
set the Matrix determinant to any number
we like we can choose a scaling number
which sets the determinant of the Matrix
two plus one
you might think that this gives us the
sl2c matrices but not quite
since overall scaling doesn't change the
transformation this means that the
positive version of a matrix is
equivalent to the negative version of
that Matrix
so this doesn't give us sl2c but instead
its projected version
so13 which is also sometimes called the
projective special linear matrices psl2c
so we see that Mobius Transformations
are equivalent to Lorenz Transformations
so13 on spinners
now these double covers of the rotation
and lorentz groups actually have special
names they are called spin groups
for example the double cover of SO3 is
called the group spin 3 which also
happens to be equivalent to su2
the double cover of so13 is called the
group spin 1 3 which also happens to be
equivalent to sl2c
we were able to figure out what the spin
3 and spin 1 3 groups were using
intuition and cleverness over the past
few videos once we found there were ways
to represent 3D spatial vectors and 4D
space-time vectors as two by two
matrices we ended up figuring out
through a mix of trial and error that we
could rotate the components of these two
by two matrices using double-sided
transformations
and this gave us the double covers su2
and sl2c which are also called spin 3
and spin 1 3.
but there's a more systematic way of
building these spin groups
for any Dimension n given the rotation
group son there's a systematic way of
constructing its double cover spin n
if you think of the unit length
quaternions as being the group spin 3
then the group spin n would be the
generalization of the quaternions for
any arbitrary Dimension n likewise for
any space time with p time dimensions
and Q space dimensions we have the
lorentz group sopq there's a systematic
way of constructing its double cover
spin PQ
the systematic way of constructing these
spin groups involves the use of Clifford
algebras also called geometric algebras
which is what we're going to cover in
the next few videos in the series
Clifford algebras can be thought of as
generalizations of complex numbers
quaternions and the sigma matrices as
well as the Dirac matrices from the
Dirac equation in particle physics
the key idea behind Clifford algebra's
is having symbols that square to either
plus one or minus one that also
anti-commute with each other
these simple properties let us do some
very impressive things
we normally think of scalars vectors
Spinners and the rotation operations on
these objects as being separate kinds of
objects
but in Clifford algebras all these
objects live together side by side this
doesn't give us any new math or physics
but it does let us rewrite certain
equations in math and physics in
impressively clean ways
for example it's possible to write the
four Maxwell equations of electricity
and magnetism as a single equation using
Clifford algebras
it's also possible to write the Dirac
equation Which models free Spin one-half
particles and quantum mechanics using
Clifford algebras
we can also systematically build
Spinners and Clifford algebras as well
so if you want to learn more about
Clifford algebras you can move on to the
next video spinners for beginners number
11.